Sandy Dwyer papers 1977-1991
UCLA Library Special Collections
Sandy Dwyer papers
1977-1991
2166
UCLA Library Special Collections
10.5 linear ft. (21 boxes)
Sandy Dwyer is a lesbian activist, playwright and journalist living and working in Los Angeles, California. This collection represents materials used by and produced by Sandy Dwyer in the course of her life. The bulk are scripts and promotional materials.
Dwyer, Sandy
Restrictions on Access
COLLECTION STORED OFF-SITE AT SRLF: Open for research. Advance notice required for access. Contact the UCLA Library Special Collections Reference Desk for paging information.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 7347785
Acquisition Information
Provenance unknown. This collection is part of an outreach and collection-building partnership between the June L. Mazer Lesbian Archives, the UCLA Center for the Study of Women (CSW) and the UCLA Library.
Biography
Sandy Dwyer was born Sandra Jean Nelson in Milwaukee, Wisconsin. She was raised on a ranch in the Ozarks of Missouri by her parents who were rodeo producers. She received her Masters degree at the University of Missouri. She spent time as a trapeze artist, biology teacher, trick rope artist, social worker, gardener, actor and playwrite. Sandy Dwyer came out as a lesbian in 1986 and became involved with the Los Angeles gay and lesbian community. She co-founded a newspaper focused on local gay and lesbian news and events called The News. The paper was known for its hard hitting journalism and gained notoriety for exposing financial abuses by large mainstream gay and lesbian non profit organizations.
Scope and Content
This collection contains materials used and produced by Sandy Dwyer predominantly through the 1970s and 1980s. Included are plays written by Sandy as well as programs and other promotional materials from theater productions in which she was involved. Correspondence of both a personal and professional nature are represented. Work materials from the Department of Public Social Services are also included as are research materials used for various jobs.
Dramatists, American--20th century -- Archival resources.; Dwyer, Sandy -- Archival resources.; Women journalists--United States -- Archival resources.
Container List
- T-Shirts., 1970-1989.; cotton shirts (Box 1)
  Cotton shirts from various lesbian and feminist events and organizations.
- T-Shirts., 1970-1989.; cotton shirts (Box 2)
- Radio., 1986.; printed paper, folder (Box 3, Folder 1)
  Includes an audience marketing plan for Media West Productions as well as correspondence. Also included are a sample format, program descriptions, demographics, sponsorship information and advertising rates for Sunday Brunch Radio.
- Correspondence and Newsletters., 1987.; printed paper, photocopies (Box 3, Folder 2)
  Newsletters from various gay and lesbian activist organizations, correspondence with these organizations. Also includes press releases and newspaper clippings.
- Poetry and Landscapes., 1984.; bound printed chapbooks (Box 3, Folder 3)
  Includes: Edwin: A character in Poems by Clifton Snyder with illustrations by Trent Edward Sally Warner Contemplative Landscape
- Play by Several Authors., No Date.; printed paper, handwritten notes, photocopies (Box 3, Folder 4)
  Several versions and drafts of a play written and edited collaboratively by Sandy Dwyer and a group of participants. Titles vary.
- Play by Several Authors., No Date.; printed paper, handwritten notes, photocopies (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Play by Several Authors., No Date.; printed paper, handwritten notes, photocopies (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Play by Several Authors., No Date.; printed paper, handwritten notes, photocopies (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Dog Calendar., 1984.; glossy printed calendar (Box 4, Folder 1)
  A 1984 calendar featuring dogs published by Alyson Publications.
- Photos (1)., 1981-1989.; photos of varying sizes and print techniques (Box 4, Folder 2)
  Photographs of various plays, films, cultural events and speeches that featured gay or lesbian characters, gay or lesbian entertainment professionals and gay or lesbian luminaries.
- Photos (2)., 1981-1989.; photos of varying sizes and print techniques (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Photos (3)., 1981-1989.; photos of varying sizes and print techniques (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Photos (4)., 1981-1989.; photos of varying sizes and print techniques (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Magazines and Newspapers (1)., 1980-1987.; stapled printed paper (Box 5, Folder 2)
  Laguna Outreach: August 1987 Volume 6 Number 8 November 1987 Volume 8, Number 11 The Lesbian News: January 1980 Volume 5, Number 6 March 1980 Volume 5, Number 8 April 1980 Volume 5, Number 9 The Optimist: A Publication of AIDS Project Los Angeles: November 1986 Number 23
- Magazines and Newspapers (2)., 1983-1986.; stapled newsprint (Box 5, Folder 3)
  LA Times Magazine: October 5, 1986 West Hollywood The Paper: December 1985 Volume 1, Number 17 Southern California Women for Understanding Newsletter: October, November 1987 Volume 2, Number 5 The Lesbian News: March 1984 Volume 9, Number 8 December 1985 Volume 9, Number 5
- Magazines and Newspapers (3)., 1980-1981.; stapled printed paper and newsprint (Box 5, Folder 4)
  Lesbian News: February 1980 Volume 5, Number 7 June 1980 Volume 5, Number 11 May 1980 Volume 5, Number 10 January 1981 Volume 6, Number 6 December 1980, Volume 6, Number 5 November 1980, Volume 6, Number 4 Also includes the Lesbian News Reference List for Southern California Women's Communityi January 1981
- Magazines and Newspapers (4)., 1982-1985.; stapled printed paper and newsprint (Box 5, Folder 5)
  Gay Milwaukee: Gay Guide to Entertainment April 1981 Coming Out to your Parents Pamphlet 1984 Washington Post Clippping November 1, 1985 "Teenage Homosexuality" Southern California Women for Understanding Newsletter October, 11, 1984 with note Lesbian News December 1982, Volume 8, Number 5 Also includes: Bumper Sticker, timesheets from Frontiers Magazine
- Magazines and Newspapers (5)., 1980-1984.; stapled printed paper and newsprint (Box 5, Folder 6)
  Southern California Women for Understanding Newsletter: February-March, 1987 Lesbian News: June 1980 Volume 5, Number 12 June 1982 Volume 7, Number 11 October 1980 Volume 6, Number 3 September 1980 Volume 5, Number 2 August 1980 Volume 6, Number 11 The Bar Rag Newsletter: September 1981 Connection: February 8-22, 1984 LA Times: November 24, 1981 Part VI Frontiers: April 11-18, 1984 Christopher Street West Bulletin
- Magazines and Newspapers (6)., 1980-1983.; stapled printed paper and newsprint (Box 5, Folder 7)
  The Lesbian News: March 1982 Volume 7 Number 8 January 1983 Volume 8, Number 6 September 1982 Volume 8, Number 2 May 1982 Volume 1, Number 10 November 1982 volume 8, Number 4 April 1982 Volume 8, Number 3 October 1982 Volume 8, Number 3 August 1982 Volume 8, Number 1 The Advocate: June 12, 1980
- T-Shirts., 1970-1989.; cotton shirts (Box 6)
- Maps-Mastercopy., No Date.; photocopies (Box 7, Folder 1)
  Photocopies of maps drawn to aid members of a softball league in getting to games.
- Correspondence., 1987-1988.; handwritten letters, printed paper, photocopies (Box 7, Folder 2)
  Correspondence with a range of people including friends, political contacts and colleagues.
- Women's History., 1986-1990.; newsprint, printed paper (Box 7, Folder 3)
  Includes a clipping from the LA Weekly June 23-29 with a short feature on Sandy Dwyer as well as a copy of The News April 4, 1986 and a copy of The Valley Business Alliance March 1990.
- Glenn Cannon Photos., 1987.; photographs (Box 7, Folder 4)
  Includes photographs, a note from Glenn Cannon to Sandy Dwyer and a business card.
- Calendars and Planners., 1975-1979.; bound calendars (Box 7, Folder 5)
  Planners from 1975, 1978, 1979.
- Department of Public Social Services (Miscellaneous)., 1976-1977.; printed paper, photocopies, stapled paper (Box 8, Folder 1)
  Includes letters, ID Cards, internal documents (time-off requests etc.), drawings.
  General note
  The original label on this folder was "Some papers from my tenure at DPSS - Medical Division. My position was Program Assistant."
- Department of Public Social Services - Sandy Dwyer., 1974-1975.; printed paper (Box 8, Folder 2)
  Original label "When with DPSS as Program Assistant in Medi-Cal - I wrote the enclosed memos and developed the forms - you can tell from initials in lower left of cover sheet - example - RLC (Program Lead:Robert L. Chaffee - one who approves): SN (Sandra Nelson - one who writes): CLL (Cynthis L. Luna - one who types it)
- Notes., 1976-1981.; greeting cards, handwritten notes, printed paper (Box 8, Folder 3)
  Jounal entries, newspaper clipping with note.
- Theatre Materials., No Date.; typewritten paper, photocopies (Box 8, Folder 4)
  Contact information, drafts of plays and press concerning different theatre projects involving Sandy Dwyer as writer/producer.
- Greeting Cards., 1971-1980.; greeting cards and envelopes (Box 8, Folder 5)
  Greeting cards.
- Alyson Publications Leonard Matlovich Dress Kit., 1989. (Box 8, Folder 6)
  Alyson Publications Leonard Matlovich Dress Kit
  Technical Sergeant Leonard P. Matlovich (July 6, 1943 – June 22, 1988)was a Vietnam War veteran, race relations instructor, and recipient of the Purple Heart and the Bronze Star. Matlovich was the first gay service member to purposely out himself to the military to fight their ban on gays.
- "Favorite Places Favorite Things" by Darel Hale., No Date.; printed paper (Box 9, Folder 1)
  Treatment for a play or monologue series.
- Flyers, Brochures, Programs., 1987-1990.; photocopies, printed paper, stapled paper, bound programs (Box 9, Folder 2)
  Brochures and programs from Los Angeles area gay, lesbian and feminist organizations.
- Behavior Studies., No Date.; handwritten notes (Box 9, Folder 3)
  Poetry as well as a draft and printed versions of the essay " A Male Homosexual's Behavior Characteristics and Their Relationship to the fulfillment of Neurotic Needs."
- Printing., 1986.; handwritten notes, printed paper (Box 9, Folder 4)
  Letters, meeting minutes and formatting mockups.
- Advertising Rates and Analysis (The News)., 1986.; handwritten notes, printed paper, brochures (Box 9, Folder 5)
  Rates and advertising analysis for the gay and lesbian newspaper founded and operated by Sandy Dwyer, The News.
- Confidential Business Plan (The News)., 1985.; typed paper (Box 9, Folder 6)
  Two copies of the confidential business plan for The News, the gay and lesbian newspaper founded and operated by Sandy Dwyer.
- Fictitious Business Report (The News)., 1986.; typed paper (Box 9, Folder 7)
  Receipts and completed forms required for filing a Fictitious Business Report along with a letter confirming status.
- Dummy Mockup (The News)., 1986.; graph paper, printed paper (Box 9, Folder 8)
  Twenty four page mockup of an issue of The News, a gay and lesbian newspaper founded and operated by Sandy Dwyer. Includes handwritten notes and pasted articles on graph paper.
- Miscellaneous (The News)., 1986.; typewritten paper, handwritten notes, newspaper clippings (Box 10, Folder 1)
  Style guide information, clippings about The News and/or other gay news outlets, mockups.
- Business Plan (The News)., 1986.; typewritten paper with handwritten notes (Box 10, Folder 2)
  Includes the business plan for The News with commentary and assistance from Ron Norman as business adviser.
- Management (The News)., 1986.; typewritten paper, handwritten notes (Box 10, Folder 3)
  Includes notes and essays about plans for the management of The News, down to a daily scale. In addition, this folder contains correspondence with different constituencies concerning management issues.
- University of Missouri., 1962-1966.; printed material, typewritten paper, onion skin paper (Box 10, Folder 4)
  Letters, resume, published reading material and essays from Sandy Dwyer's time at the University of Missouri.
- Miscellaneous., No Date.; handwritten notes, photographs, stapled paper (Box 10, Folder 5)
  Inventory, Connexxus Anniversary Program, The News Program, Miscellaneous photographs.
- Psychiatry/Women's Studies., No Date.; typewritten paper (Box 10, Folder 6)
  Assignments and research materials for academic courses in psychiatry and women's studies, mainly focused on behavior patterns of homosexuals.
- Ephemera., No Date.; miscellaneous (Box 10, Folder 7)
  Visors, buttons, visitor cards and various ephemera.
- Drafts/Edits (Miscellaneous)., No Date.; printed paper (Box 11, Folder 1)
  Contains drafts, notes and edits of miscellaneous plays. Some of the stories are complete and some are partial.
- "Cheese and Crackers"., 1980.; printed paper (Box 11, Folder 2)
  Drafts and completed versions of the play "Cheese and Crackers" by Sandy Dwyer. Also includes some promotional material, a working script with cast lists for selected performances.
- "Depressed"., No Date.; printed paper (Box 11, Folder 3)
  Drafts, edits and completed versions of the play "Depressed" by Sandy Dwyer.
- "Good Morning Dear"., No Date.; printed paper (Box 11, Folder 4)
  Contains drafts, edits and completed versions of the play "Good Morning Dear" by Sandy Dwyer.
- "Honest Encounter"., No Date.; printed paper (Box 11, Folder 5)
  Drafts and edits and completed versions of the play "Honest Encounter" written by Sandy Dwyer.
- "Hope Rings Eternal"., No Date.; printed paper (Box 11, Folder 6)
  Drafts, edits and completed versions of the play "Hope Rings Eternal" written by Sandy Dwyer.
- "Let's Get a Cat"., No Date.; printed paper (Box 11, Folder 7)
  Drafts, edits and completed versions of the play "Let's Get a Cat" by Sandy Dwyer.
- "Loot"., No Date.; printed paper (Box 11, Folder 8)
  Promotional materials for the play "Loot."
- "Man and Woman"., No Date.; printed paper (Box 11, Folder 9)
  Drafts, edits and completed versions of the play "Man and Woman" written by Sandy Dwyer.
- "Pissoire"., No Date.; printed paper (Box 12, Folder 1)
  Drafts, edits and completed versions of the play "Pissoire" by Sandy Dwyer.
- "Pleased to Meet You"., No Date.; printed paper (Box 12, Folder 2)
  Drafts, edits and completed versions of the play "Pleased to Meet You" by Sandy Dwyer.
- Newspapers - REviews., 1980-1982.; newsprint (Box 12, Folder 3)
  Newspapers and newspaper clippings that contain reviews of plays written by or featuring Sandy Dwyer in some capacity.
- "Romantic Interlude"., No Date.; printed paper (Box 13, Folder 1)
  Drafts, edits and completed versions of the play "Romantic Interlude" by Sandy Dwyer.
- "They are Soft and Cuddly"., No Date.; printed paper (Box 13, Folder 2)
  Drafts, edits and completed versions of the play "They are Soft and Cuddly" by Sandy Dwyer.
- "Wish on the Moon"., No Date.; printed paper (Box 13, Folder 3)
  Drafts, edits and completed version so of the play "Wish on the Moon" by Sandy Dwyer.
- Unnamed Play Edits., No Date.; printed paper with handwritten notes (Box 13, Folder 4)
  Notes and edits on an unnamed play by Sandy Dwyer.
- Correspondence (Apollo's Mice)., 1979-1982.; printed paper, handwritten notes (Box 13, Folder 5)
  Correspondence with theaters concerning possible productions and stagings of plays associated with the Apollo's Mice Theatre Company.
  Sandy Dwyer was a member and featured actor/writer involved with Apollo's Mice Theatre Company.
- Apollo's Mice Theatre Company Materials., 1982-1985.; flyers, printed paper, photographs (Box 13, Folder 6)
  Includes programs and promotional materials for the play "Cheese and Crackers" by Sandy Dwyer as well as programs for "Grab Bag Cabaret," "Perfect Relationship," and "Haunted Host" which each featured Sandy Dwyer. This folder also contains Sandy Dwyer's headshots, reviews for several of the plays and a flyer for the Orange County Gay and Lesbian Resource Day.
- "Cheese and Crackers" (2)., No Date.; bound printed paper (Box 13, Folder 7)
  Three copies of the play "Cheese and Crackers" by Sandy Dwyer.
- Correspondence - Theatre (Miscellaneous)., 1974-1977.; printed paper, envelopes, onion skin paper (Box 14, Folder 1)
  Includes correspondence regarding productions, theatrical events and education.
- Correspondence - Personal (Miscellaneous)., 1974-1980.; printed paper, handwritten letters (Box 14, Folder 2)
  Correspondence with friends and colleagues, the bulk are greeting cards sent for birthday or holiday celebrations.
- Correspondence - Personal (Miscellaneous) 2., 1974-1980.; printed paper, handwritten letters, greeting cards (Box 14, Folder 3)
  Correspondence with friends, colleagues and family. The majority is made up of greeting cards.
- Correspondence - Danella., 1982-1983.; handwritten letters (Box 14, Folder 4)
  Correspondence with Sandy Dwyer and her lover Danella. Some of the letters include annotations on letters from Danella by Sandy.
- Production Book for Bye Bye Birdie., No Date.; photocopies (Box 15, Folder 1)
  Production book used by Sandy Dwyer for a production of Bye Bye Birdie.
- Headshots and CAA contracts., No Date.; photographs, printed paper (Box 15, Folder 2)
  Headshots from different points in Sandy Dwyer's acting career, some under the name of Sandra Nelson. Also included are signed contracts with agents and actor's unions.
- Production Book for Talent Debut., No Date.; printed paper (Box 15, Folder 3)
  Production book used by Sandy Dwyer in a production of Talent Debut.
- Miscellaneous Scripts., No Date.; printed paper (Box 15, Folder 4)
  Miscellaneous scripts, no attribution or participation is noted or indicated on the scripts.
- Actor's Workshop., 1984.; printed paper, envelopes (Box 15, Folder 5)
  Programs, class information, newsletters and reviews from the Actor's Workshop.
  Founded by Film/TV actor R.J. Adams in 1980, The Actors Workshop has been training aspiring and professional young film/television actors in both Los Angeles and Orange County, California.
- "A Waltz for Women's Voices"., 1976.; printed paper (Box 15, Folder 6)
  Sandy Dwyer was cast in this play as the narrator but it never opened. Contained are working scripts.
- "The Blonde in Twenty B"., 1981.; printed paper (Box 15, Folder 7)
  Working script for Sandy Dwyer, who was cast in the role of Bernice.
- Theatrical Leaflets., 1979-1985.; flyers, printed paper (Box 15, Folder 8)
  Flyers and leaflets for various productions.
- "Newspaper Clippings"., 1980-1987.; printed paper, newsprint (Box 15, Folder 9)
  Reviews of shows and other media mentions of Sandy Dwyer.
- "Crisis Counselor"., 1982.; printed paper (Box 15, Folder 10)
  Script and correspondence about the public service announcement "Crisis Counselor" in which Sandy Dwyer was cast as a lesbian mother involved in a custody battle.
- Theater Company Proposal., No Date.; printed paper (Box 15, Folder 11)
  Proposal and accompanying notes as well as correspondence written by Sandy Dwyer. The proposal was for a gay and lesbian theater company in Los Angeles.
- Softball League., 1970.; handwritten notes (Box 16, Folder 1)
  Notes, statistics and information about the softball league in which Sandy Dwyer participated.
- Correspondence - Personal (3)., 1970-1989.; greeting cards (Box 16, Folder 2)
  Greeting cards sent to Sandy Dwyer.
- Correspondence - Personal (4)., 1970-1989.; greeting cards (Box 16, Folder 3)
- Logo (The News)., 1986.; handwritten notes, drawings, collage (Box 16, Folder 4)
  Logo for the gay and lesbian magazine founded and operated by Sandy Dwyer.
- Miscellaneous., No Date.; drawings, notebooks (Box 16, Folder 5)
  Notebooks of poetry from former lovers of Sandy Dwyer, personal calendars and drawings.
- Frontiers Magazine., 1985.; newsprint, printed paper (Box 16, Folder 6)
  Articles written by Sandy Dwyer as well as photographs taken by Sandy Dwyer that were commissioned by or featured in Frontiers Magazine.
- Poetry (Notebook)., 1963-1978.; handwritten notes (Box 17, Folder 1)
  Poetry drafts and edits from two different notebooks in the collection.
- Poetry (Rough Drafts)., 1968-1977.; typewritten paper with handwritten notes (Box 17, Folder 2)
  Rough drafts of a poetry series written by Sandy Dwyer.
- Poetry (Originals)., 1978.; printed paper (Box 17, Folder 3)
  Poetry series by Sandy Dwyer, marked by her as "Originals."
- "Once Upon a Lifetime" Poetry Collection., 1974.; printed paper (Box 17, Folder 4)
  Poetry collection written by Sandy Dwyer.
- Department of Public Social Services (DPSS)., 1969-1976.; printed paper, invoices, cards (Box 17, Folder 5)
  Employment records, test results, applications and resumes from Sandy Dwyer's tenure at the DPSS. This included time spent as a social worker, analyst and program assistant.
- Certificates., 1971-1977.; printed paper (Box 17, Folder 6)
  Certificate of appreciation from the city in appreciation of Sandy Dwyer's service on a jury as well as a certificate recognizing her participation in a softball league.
- Poetry (Typed Drafts)., 1968-1977.; printed paper (Box 18, Folder 1)
  Typed drafts of various pieces of poetry collections by Sandy Dwyer.
- Essays., No Date. (Box 18, Folder 2)
  "Jeans", "Labels", "Moments" and "Why I Write, all essays by Sandy Dwyer.
- Medical Handbook., 1972.; printed paper (Box 18, Folder 3)
  Medical handbook partially compiled by Sandy Dwyer.
- Information and Referral Directory., 1974.; bound paper (Box 18, Folder 4)
  Directory containing listings of medical and psychological services.
- Poetry (Rewrites)., 1978.; printed paper (Box 18, Folder 5)
  Rewrites of poetry from a collection by Sandy Dwyer.
- Radio Scripts (1)., 1989.; typed paper (Box 19, Folder 1)
  Scripts for radio program "This Way Out."
  "This Way Out" is a weekly half-hour community radio program produced by and for LGBT people and their equality allies. The "magazine style" show is heard on more than 200 local stations around the world, via satellite to cable and home receivers in Europe, Asia, Africa, and the Middle East, and online via our podcasts (click on the link in the upper right-hand corner).
- Radio Scripts (2)., 1989.; typed paper (Box 19, Folder 2)
  Scripts for the radio program "This Way Out."
- Radio Scripts (3)., 1989.; typed paper (Box 19, Folder 3)